If you want to maximize the time. Okay.
I'm going to mute myself.
Okay.
Welcome, everybody.
It is my great pleasure to be here
with friends and collaborators.
Mandy Canales, who is a wonderful
theater and dance teacher
at Washington State University,
and my longtime writing buddy,
Marc Moreno.
He was waving in two screens,
if you can follow him,
who teaches writing at USC?
And we are sharing with you
what we've been playing
with recently, which is
doing using yet another digital platform.
As we migrate from platform to platform
with the the able
tutoring of the wonderful Mandy
to expand one of our recent net props.
So let me just introduce you
to the basic concept and what we're doing
with this piece.
So in the current
situation,
least here in the United States,
one of the clichés of journalism
is to call things unprecedented.
And sadly, I have to agree
that many of the things, in fact,
maybe most of the things
that are happening amongst
the rich and powerful
are entirely predictable
and happened century
after century in the same ways.
And that's why we're turning
to the ancient comedia dell'arte.
For some relief, this was inspired for me
the project our our net profit Comedia
del net profit, inspired by Mikhail
Bulgakov, Russian writer in the early 20th
century, did a biography of Moliere
and it was in a sense
an also an autobiography
because both Moliere and Bulgakov
were under the thumb of tyrants, Moliere
under the thumb of Louis the 14th
and Bulgakov under the thumb of Stalin,
and they in his book
he admires his predecessor and talks
about strategies for satire
in very repressive surveillance societies.
So what is that problem?
It has various definitions,
but whenever we talk about it,
we show this slide,
which is a comedian vision.
It is collaborative playfulness,
improvised literature
in real time, in digital means.
And this is sort of the technical literary
definition that we use these days.
It's a practice that we it's not
just something we invented by any means.
It's something we see all over.
There's been many presentations already
at this about similar projects that live
in somewhere in this Venn diagram
between different existing disciplines.
A quick example of a neat prov
is to pretend with your friends
in social media
that you're going without your technology,
and then you spend and call it one week,
no tech, and then spend a week complaining
about how much you miss your machine
and having pictures, self-aggrandizing
pictures of you getting away from it
all out in the countries.
My own background that built up to net
profit was in being involved
in a crowdsourced novel in the 1980s
in Seattle, and that's me on the right
with Rock in the 80s, mustache
and Out in the world in costume
as a as basically kind of performance art,
going up to people and saying, hey,
we're building a novel.
Can we borrow a few of your words
and then writing down what they're saying,
putting them in a vast database
that we knew even then had to somehow
be organized on computers
because we'd never be able
to keep it organized otherwise.
This is the beautiful sculptural
Charizard two
that was built for us by the sculptor
Claire Colquitt,
and we invited people
to come in, contribute at the Bumbershoot
Arts Festival to edit,
and that was really revealing to us.
We turned over the keys
to a collaborative work of collaborative
literature to people edit on the walls,
and these were the clues.
It was a mystery story.
And here are the clues in these vitrines.
And it was tremendous fun.
It was the most fun
I had and kind of freed me personally from
a vision of what it is to be
a writer that had to do with loneliness
and and slaving away.
This was more, much more fun to do things
collaboratively.
So there is a version of that project
in the form of a book, one
of an infinite number
of possible versions of a database novel.
And there's a description of that project
and other early experimentation
where we began to write online
in this book,
another example of a deeper
problem is I work for the web,
where Mark played a tycoon
in his wonderful word,
the person who owns the entire internet.
And they're just having a nice campaign
to congratulate everybody
for all the free work that they do for
for the for the internet.
And in the process of publicizing that
campaign, people realize
that they're being taken advantage of
and they start a union.
This is a union poster
made by the wonderful talent Mehmet.
And there began to be again,
kind of performance micro performances
as people photograph their hands,
either voting forms up for the union,
and then the company would turn that
same image into thumbs down for the union.
There's talons.
Talons, character link. Din
died,
and then LinkedIn's ghost reappeared.
And this is a talons thing.
And there was a ended with a walkout
where a fingertip
walkout where people walked away
from doing free work for the internet.
So those kinds of experiments,
our other net profits are described
in this book, which is free
on the internet, open access,
and describes a ton of projects.
So what we're going to do today
is kind of what we always like to do.
It's our favorite thing to do,
and that is to experiment
and try to find new kinds of beauty.
And in this case, as I said,
we're being inspired by committee,
which seemed to us a response,
a satirical response
to current events without being specific,
sort of for two reasons.
Like there for me, there's other people
that can do the specific satire
better than than I can,
but also in a truly repressive society,
it's safer.
Do you always reserve the possibility,
say, oh, no, sir, this is not hope, Evans.
You're wonderful.
This is not at all about this
character is not at all about you.
This is an old fashioned thing that people
have been doing for hundreds of years.
And you're just so contemporary,
so committed.
Daylight.
Some scholars believe,
and I'd like to believe, that
it goes all the way back to the ancient
world of the Greeks and Romans.
They're not really sure about that
for 100% sure, but it is very, very old.
And these characters have been traveling
in their masks for a lot of years.
It's an outdoor form of theater as opposed
to kind of the elite indoor theater.
It takes place in marketplaces, carnivals,
and has a stock set of characters,
very physical.
These are, you know, every each generation
adapts the characters.
And the thing that's interesting
in terms of contemporary color,
one of the many things that's interesting
in terms of contemporary culture is that
it is improvised.
There are what we're called scenarios.
In fact, I believe the word scenario comes
from this practice and community
art of writing down just that, you know, 2
or 3 page outline of the story,
but then the actual lines
and everything was improvised on the spot.
And Committee dell'Arte
was one of the things that Del Close
and other American theater students
relied heavily on
when they kind of invented modern improv.
The modern improv theater techniques
were very much based on this idea
of the improvising actor.
So it continues to this day.
You can see traditional things,
performances that try to sort of
historical reenactments,
but part of the tradition of the comedia
is to always include obliquely,
never directly
but obliquely include current events
in the old, old characters
and old situations.
So these are just some examples
of both high
end productions and local group,
local theater group productions.
And for those of you
who are familiar with pantomime,
there are Christmas panto
in the British tradition.
That is the English version of comedy.
And it's it's
a, you know, each generation, each country
adapts it,
but you'll recognize the standard
characters
completely in contemporary panto things.
So what we did was,
since we love writing together in real
time, is we built a game, a creative game
where you where in an hour or two,
a group of friends
can get together on zoom and in Google Doc
or in person in a Google Doc,
which is really fun and write together.
And these are just some images
of one such community session
where one of the authors is
reading her character description
and cracking everybody up.
And then people
are we do do some writing, and it's
similar in lots of ways to D&D, where
you kind of go back and forth
between being in character
and then talking at a metal level
about your character and strategizing,
do you want me to do this?
Is it okay if I do that?
And it ends after each act
you read out loud together in?
It's hilarious and fond,
and I highly recommend it as a practice.
But then we met Mandy
and it's like she was saying, well,
what if it included also VR aspects
and that blue our minds and we said yes,
yes, yes and jumped on board with that.
And so when Mandy is going to be the
the major presenter
in our workshop,
but she's going to teach us
about physical enactments
in VR of these characters.
So this is very simplified.
This is just marks and my simplification.
But the
character categories of comedia are these
the big wigs, the lovers and the goofballs
or the goofball worker bees.
So characterize the big wigs,
have a reasonably high sense
of self-importance and require constant
admiration.
They feel they deserve privileges
and special treatment.
They expect to be recognized as superior
even without achievements.
They expect other people
to do what they want without questioning.
They have an inability or unwillingness
to recognize
the needs and feelings of others,
and they react with
this is I don't know you, but
this is sounding really familiar to me.
I don't know
if you recognize these traits.
Oh shoot. I'm sorry.
My mistake. These are.
This is not a committed thing.
This is the Mayo Clinic description
of narcissistic personality disorder.
Sorry.
So scratch that.
The the big wigs, as Mark
and I define it, are
have these characteristics and are broadly
are kind of the miser Pantalone.
And again linguists
some linguists, many linguists
claim that our word pants and for trousers
in is from the character Pantalone
because he he was very vain
about his skinny old man legs,
and would prance around in red tights.
The know it all.
Who is the data
which is essentially the professor,
even though he does traditionally love
to give bad medical advice.
And the vision of the early scenes
scene of where Comedia takes
place is at the marketplace.
And so they're up.
They have a bench and they mount it.
They get up on top of the bench
and they are therefore mountebank
that that's what that word means.
And next on the next bench might be a
snake oil salesman selling fake medicine.
So it's all part of that same thing.
And then there's the bragging coward
who wears a fancy uniform but runs and
and shrieks whenever there's danger
and hides behind somebody else.
In the middle are the lovers. They're.
They're wonderful.
They're the characters in Comedia
that are without masks.
And generally in any given troupe,
they would be the ones,
the best looking young pair
that's there, the romantic leads.
And here we begin to see that
these characters really continue,
even outside of strictly comedia
dell'arte related things.
These are the stock characters,
for example, of American sitcoms,
as you see them as such.
And then there are the Zanni.
So the Zanes are the servants
of the bigwigs or the servants of the
and sometimes the lovers.
And our word
zany comes from this word zany.
And there are lots of different types
and again,
customized by actors in each generation.
But there's kind of a foolish prankster
harlequin character.
There's the super people person
who is always learning about everybody
and helping and gossiping,
and then the schemer who's,
you know,
sort of the head of the petty criminals.
So at this point, I am going to turn it
over to Mark and Mandy.
I'm going to encourage you
to use Gallery View
and Pinning to get a good view of this.
And we might even want to do that
in the official recording.
Would be great.
And I will get into
both character
and VR and join them shortly.
All right.
Thank you Rob. Fantastic.
That's such a good breakdown.
I love hearing
about the different characters,
because you can absolutely
look at modern day
TV and sitcoms and see that
these particular archetypes have gone
through the entire history of the world
and have made it to our screens to today.
So the next time you watch a sitcom,
see if you can pick out any of those
characters because they're probably there.
That's my favorite thing to tell students.
Okay, so hello, I'm Mandy, I,
I do work at Washington State,
but I don't teach theater and dance.
I teach theater and dance in VR.
So at the VR Dance Academy
and I teach improv as well in VR.
I am at Washington State University
in the Digital Technology
and Culture program,
but I do try to bring in all this stuff
into my classes as much as I can.
So I guess sometimes I do teach theater
and dance at Washington State.
So real quick,
we are working with technology
that probably shouldn't
be working together like we are
crossing wires that shouldn't be crossed.
So if there's any kind of technical issue
or glitch, we will just work with it.
Please stay with us.
And yes, I do know Deanie.
Deanie actually introduced me
to Rob and Mark.
So anyway, back to the crossing wires.
I am in zoom and I'm in VR.
I'm using OBS.
I'm doing a lot of things because of that.
You'll notice
that my mouth isn't moving in VR.
My mouth normally works in VR, but
I need to cut off certain audio things.
So this.
And then also when I have my screen up
and I'm looking at zoom,
my fingers don't work.
So normally
my fingers do work, I'm able to move them.
So I just wanted to indicate those things
so that you get an understanding that
sometimes, you know, when we when we add
technologies on top of each other,
we get some things that just don't work
the way we really need them to work.
And I want to be transparent about that
because I know somebody would be like,
her mouth isn't moving.
Yeah, because my audio is not on
because then it would be a wall of sound
that would be very uncomfortable
for everybody.
So this is my studio.
This is my studio space.
We won't be able to look at it all,
but you will get an understanding.
Within my space in VR chat, I have a
a black box theater,
a theater in the round,
and you'll be seeing our studio
theater and I hold classes in here
from time to time, mainly teaching improv,
or when I'm producing
other teachers classes in this space.
I've produced a Shakespeare 360 class
and have also done comedia training
in these classrooms.
It's just like a regular classroom.
This is VR, so we could do lots of things.
We could go to the forest, we could go
to a castle, we could go anywhere we want.
But I feel as an educator,
if you're learning something new,
you should really just maybe be
in some space that your brain
can understand
so that you can focus on the basics.
So I create a space that is very similar
to what you would see in in real life.
And so we just have some basic stuff
and I feel it
helps students understand the technique.
And then when they get a little bit
solid foundation,
then we can go out into the world
and and do more immersive performances.
So if you have a question of okay,
so why are you doing this
in a regular studio?
That's why your brain, everyone's
brain, is going wild.
When they put on a headset,
they don't really know what to do with it.
So I like to try and scale it
back and say, okay,
you understand what a studio is, and
and you can show up here
and feel comfortable.
So you see Mark behind me.
Hello.
And and then Rob is on his way.
What I want you all to do is
I want you to be really observant.
Between all of our real life,
I don't like to say
real life, but like, our physical,
our physical boxes and
what it looks like,
how it's translating in VR.
Because this is the big deal.
When I first got into VR, I was
it was during Covid,
and just like a lot of people,
I got into VR during Covid
and I realized that I had been performing
improv and sketch comedy and in VR,
a lot of things weren't translating.
I have a, you know, the the face that
I use isn't as expressive as it could be.
My body at the time,
I only had three point tracking,
so it wasn't as expressive or I didn't
understand how to use it at the time.
And so I was thinking, what is the best
way to maybe break this down?
And as I was talking to people,
it came up that mask work
is probably the best way
to really break down how to exist
in this space
and emote and communicate better.
If you notice, I'm using my hands a lot,
that absolutely helps communicate.
But other things like tilting your head
and leaning forward also helps.
But the problem is, the avatars
that we have don't always imitate,
don't always look
like our physical bodies, and we can get
a little confused as actors in VR of
what is actually being shown.
So I could bend over, but
maybe my avatar moves away, moves
in a way that I don't expect it.
So what I've done is I've taken comedian
training and kind of picked out
the different parts that would really help
somebody understand
what their physical avatar
looks like, or their physical body
looks like compared to their avatar.
And we will explore during these games.
I want you all to explore as well,
because I think it's just, well, it's fun.
You're just sitting there.
You might as well.
And when else can we get a little weird
and silly, other than being on zoom in a
theater workshop, so.
Oh, there's Rob.
So we have Rob right now.
And like I said, I want you
to just make sure you're checking
checking out the physical physical of Mark
and Rob versus their avatar in here.
You can check me out,
but I have three point
or five point tracking, so it's pretty.
What I do here is very representative.
What they're going to be doing
is three point tracking.
So it's just their hands in their head.
Rob is sitting and Mark is standing.
So they are going to be having to
move their bodies
in different ways to communicate
what they really want
to communicate in these exercises.
So since they're both here right now
and everybody is ready to go,
let's go into the classroom
and see what we can do here.
Now, again, I'm
I'm crossing a lot of wires here.
If I don't look at the camera,
I apologize.
Or if the camera gets a little weird,
I will adjust it.
I have my eye on the zoom,
but sometimes things get a little weird.
I'm not always used to using a camera
in VR on zoom, so be patient,
I appreciate it.
All right,
let's go. Let's go to the workshop.
so here's my space.
It's a modest space.
All right.
So I have a pen here.
I'm going to show you folks
where you probably need to stand.
So workers.
Ish you don't have
to stand on those specifically,
but just in that area.
Yeah.
Let's see if we got a good shot of them.
You can kind of see them.
That's a that's good enough.
Hey. Okay.
Maybe.
Sorry sorry sorry.
Yeah.
You know.
All right.
So first of all,
when I have a class,
we always like to make sure that our,
my students are happy in the avatar
that that they've chosen.
So I'm going to I'm going to have Mark
and Rob choose a couple avatars.
I came in with this,
but I want to show you
the different kinds of avatars
that you could choose.
So Mark and Rob,
why don't you just pick a couple avatars,
just cycle through
and show folks what they can be?
So here we go.
There's Mark in a weird like.
This is my more business.
He won. I'm your problem solver.
I work for it.
Hey that's fine.
We know we can change different.
I think Mark's got it.
Just happen here in this virtual space.
So as you can see,
we can change your avatars
and it instantly can change your voice
in your attitude
towards, you know, how you're speaking
and your movements.
Even so,
I found this to be really interesting.
When you change avatars, it actually
and you have a mirror.
So these folks, we do have a mirror here
that they're looking at
and they can see what their,
their avatars look like.
I'll go ahead and swing around real quick
so you can see that.
But there's the mirror.
I should
mention that my knees have started
to hurt in this avatar so much.
Okay, we gotta change it.
We gotta change it.
Okay?
No, Mark, don't let it get to you.
Okay, so that's another problem, right?
Sometimes we become our avatars.
All right.
So we're going to do a basic warmup
because and this is what I always
what I always do with my students.
And I'll go ahead and be in the camera
a little bit.
So I'm talking to you. Oh there it is. Hi.
So I normally have a warm up
with my students because it's theater.
That's what you got to do.
But also because we have these like two,
2 pound toasters
on our heads and like, it's not normal.
The fact that I can dance in
this is not normal.
It's a superpower that you have.
No, it's not a superpower.
It is a tolerance.
Try doing a pair wet in these.
It's not pretty. And it's very hard.
So the thing is that people forget
is that you still have to warm up.
You still have to do all the things
that you do when you're about to perform.
So let's just go ahead
and send away from the camera.
Let's do our circles to the right
with our head.
Just just warm up your head a little bit
your neck and then to the left.
Yeah.
And audience do the same thing. Yeah.
And then if you want to say yes. Yes.
And then no just stretching.
Let's do our shoulders.
The shoulders are going to have
a lot of tension because of the headset.
So you got to shake it out.
And then I highly recommend
shaking them out.
If you do a long session of this to just
pay attention to your body afterwards.
And then just a little
there we go.
Now folks with three point tracking
forget the rest of their body sometimes.
So I don't I don't mind if you don't have.
Just go ahead and kick your legs up
a little bit and then Rob
since you're sitting
maybe just like bring your knees up
just so you're aware of them,
this is going to affect everything else.
I always tell my students,
your brain has to be reminded that
the avatar is not your your actual body.
And so you have to be very careful.
And speaking of careful,
let's just do a really quick check.
Since we have been moving around
a little bit, can you Rob and Mark
just lift your headsets
just to check your space around?
You just want to make sure
you're not going to run into anything.
I mentioned earlier that like,
even though I have been in VR for,
I don't know, for many years and up to
almost 3000 hours, I still run into walls.
So think about that now.
The next thing I want us to do
is our vocal warm up.
So we're just going to
just do a little like 40
hot tea.
Hot tea. Yeah.
Party car.
Patchy car, potty car.
Now a little bit of a lip trill.
And then a tongue roll.
If I can do that, I can only say that
if I say the word guitar.
Hold on.
The guitar. Guitar, guitar.
Okay, fantastic.
People online are laughing,
but they really knows what they're
laughing.
Yeah. Everybody.
Everybody, please.
You please feel free to partake.
Okay, so this next this next I'm
going to stand up for the camera.
Now, this next game that I want to
or want you all to look at.
And while an absolutely join us
in doing this
because I think it's a really interesting
physical comedy exploration,
if you're not doing it with us, or
if you can keep your eye on Mark and Rob
and their avatars, please do so because
check how their body in real life is going
to probably be different in the VR space,
but also,
maybe they might come up with some things
as they're looking at themselves
that will look good as an avatar,
but weird in their physical body, right?
So we're going to play this game
called emotions one through five,
where I will state an emotion and we will
start off one as the lowest
indicator of that emotion
and go to five in a physical.
In physical comedy classes
this can go 1 to 10.
But I, I found that in VR, going 1
to 10 is just too much right now.
So 1 to 5 is good.
That's where people feel comfortable
exploring because they feel pretty limited
for some reason.
Go to 11 maybe.
Maybe one day. Yes.
Okay, so let's try this.
Emotions one through five.
Let's go emotion.
Let's start off happy.
We're all happy. It's a good day.
Happy at one.
Happy at two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
Happier five.
Yeah.
So this is really interesting
I'm not going to say anything.
I'm going to see if the
if you all caught this.
But did you notice something different
between Mark and Rob
and their avatars in that happy five.
And go ahead just shout it out.
Anybody who's watching.
So what was really interesting
and that's fine if you didn't notice,
is that Rob turned around,
turned his avatar around at five.
Go ahead Rob, do that again,
but did not move.
So Rob was not moving, but his avatar was.
And then Mark, what did you do?
Well, I was doing two things.
I was moving my tail,
which looks like this. Hold on.
It's kind of weird looking on camera,
I think.
Hold on.
There it is.
Look at my tail.
So Mark doesn't have a tail in real life.
And I would jump down.
And jumped.
So we have these two actions
now that don't need
actual physical movement.
So turning around and jumping.
And these are avatar animations
that are built into the avatars.
And you can get wild.
You can do a lot of other things.
People dance.
There's other animations
where you can do a backflip, but
I find this to be really interesting
that while sometimes people think that VR
is a limiting factor
in how you show your emotion,
these particular emotions
can be shown a lot
further than maybe in real life.
So in real life, we don't know.
Maybe Rob can't turn around that fast.
Maybe Mark can't jump.
Maybe there is. Maybe you can't do it.
That yeah, maybe you can't do a backflip.
But in VR you can.
So they're.
Pushing a button on your controllers.
Yeah. Okay.
Well,
and what's weird is when I wag my tail,
it's ridiculous looking
because I have to pull up a menu.
Well, there are a lot of restraints.
Yes, but you're wagging your tail.
You don't have a tail.
So. Fantastic.
Let's give them a round of applause
because this is wild.
So this next this next game
that we're going to play.
And this is also a physical comedy
game and it's called
I actually I actually don't know
what it's called, I named it,
but I just named it after the actions.
I think there's an actual title,
but I was just like, oh, this is what is
this is what we're going to call it. So
this is push, pull, pause, pivot.
This is when we have two actors
who are going to be negotiating
what to do with a box, everything from how
how heavy the box is or how light
the box is, or if the box is tall,
if it's small, if it's big,
everything having to do with that
and they are going to push
this box, they are going to pull the box.
They're going to pause
trying to figure out what to do with it.
And the pivot is changing
the whole strategy.
Now they're doing this without any audio.
So this is really focused
on making connection
between the two actors
that are performing.
And for efficiency sakes guys
I'm just going to call push pull,
pause pivot because this is the kind
of game that could last for hours.
I mean, there's probably
like a silent movie that is just this.
So I will make sure to call it out.
But the point is to do this with your
your partner
so you can establish
some kind of connection to each other
and get that mind
meld that we want during improv.
All right. So
we're going to start it off.
For folks already.
And then I'm going to try to frame
you up a little bit better
okay.
So guys you got a box.
What's going on with it.
Yeah.
Push.
Pull.
Okay.
Pause.
This isn't working.
Pivot.
New plan.
Is that an acting critique
or is that a no.
Pivot?
Pivot the last.
Wait.
What are we doing?
We're gonna pivot. Wait.
Pivot pivot.
Throw it up in the air.
Give him a round of applause.
That was like a silly Putty box.
Like the way you were pulling.
You snapped back.
What did some
what did other people see in that?
What did you think was going on?
Just just jump in and
and share your thoughts.
It seemed easier in this
to work against each other,
rather than with each other,
as you would in a shared physical space.
Yes. Anything else?
Do we see anything else?
Now, Alyssa, speak more about that then.
This is a really interesting observation.
I wanted to see if someone would build
on that, but let's let's take it away.
Yeah.
Like I've played this game before
in physical comedy classes and workshops.
And usually you find ways to work together
or at least play off of each other.
But I think having the virtual space,
you have to really be paying attention
to where you are in that virtual space
as your avatar.
And I feel like not it would be difficult,
I think, having not done this, to
connect to your physical body
with, like the physicality of your avatar
and spatially where you are in relation
to the other players.
Yes, yes.
And also because, I mean,
I have played this in, in real life
and the things that
are lost are the nuances. So
you can't see each other's eyes,
you can't see each other's,
maybe somebody is going
or but they're
but they're not doing it that extensively.
So they're going right.
And in real life you can see that.
And then you pick up on it
because you're like, hey, that okay,
I know what they're doing.
But in this space
you have to find new ways to communicate.
So if you do want to do the big huff
suddenly instead of going,
it's.
You know, real big.
And so that's why I think Comedia works
with this, because it was designed to hit
a crowd of hundreds of people,
so that even the people in the back
could understand
what's happening on the stage.
And so as you work with your partners
in VR, you start understanding
what those cues are.
So you start understanding what
that person looks like when they're going.
Home or.
What, you know, getting really angry or,
you know, if they shake their fists
or if they or they shake their head
to all these things that you start
learning with your colleagues
when you start playing with them,
or which is very similar
to physical comedy
and improv, you start understanding
like everybody's little,
little quirks and
and things that they bring to the table.
And so you do have all that transferable
skill within the virtual space,
but it's just with that additional, oh,
I need to communicate this a little more.
So moving on.
We're going to get to the comedia part
I promise.
So what we're going to do is we are going
we've already talked about actually,
we haven't really gone
into who these characters are.
So let's talk about who
these who Marc and Rob are playing.
So we have character.
One is that
and Rob is going to be playing zany Rob.
Do you want to talk about zany
or do you want me to talk about zany?
Okay, so
the zany are kind of
the low status characters
now, the low status characters in comedy,
they're the ones we're rooting for
right there, the everyman.
They're the people that we connect with.
They're the ones who are kind
of pulling the rug
from the high status characters, right?
We never want to see them in a sad place.
We're always saying underdog.
So the zany are a group of people,
and generally
they're servants of the high class people.
And you have a couple different styles.
You have Arlecchino, who is basically
a man child and does stupid things
all the time, but then that one time
he is a genius just pulls it off.
He's always doing acrobats
all around the place,
and he's the most physical of the zany.
But I'm not.
I'm not saying that this is my opinion,
because I know people
probably have PhDs on that, so I. Don't.
Want. To say that for sure, but in.
My opinion, are like, you know,
has that tendency to be more acrobatic.
And then you have other ones like pyro
and you have Columbine, who are always
like solving things and also just
they have their own stock character.
Rob, I believe you're leaning more towards
the Arlequin side of things.
So we'll go with that with the silly,
silly man who will do one
genius thing once in a while
to save the day.
And then Mark, you're playing IL Capitan,
which is part of the USC
event, and many apologies.
Anybody who actually speaks Italian
because I just slaughtered these words.
I do have a friend who is Italian,
and I was was reading off
these words to her and she's like.
No, no, like, stop it, stop talking.
So let.
Me know if I'm just
totally butchering these words.
But the Vecchio are the old men,
the old men in in the stories.
And IL is the braggart, right?
He is the one who says he.
He has always been
in charge, leading the charge in battle.
But actually he's the one
who's kind of slipping away, right?
Making sure that he was hiding in a bunker
while everyone else was fighting.
And then he walked away with the stories.
And so we're looking at at a man
who likes to brag about his his heroism,
but actually ends up being very cowardly.
So what we're going
to do is we are going to play
emotions one through
five using these character types.
And so this is something that I do
with my students in my class is
they'll find a character type,
and then they will see how their emotions
translate through
that particular character, which is right.
Right.
Because like we all have different ways
of expressing
ourselves as happy,
but we're all different people.
We always hear the phrase
people grieve differently, right?
And that's that's the same thing
with everyone's happy differently,
sad differently, and especially
as archetypes, because these archetypes
have to travel, they have to travel
to the audience who's watching them.
And in our case, we have to kind of break
free of these avatars, or we have to find
the opportunities that we have
in the limitations of these avatars.
So we're going to play emotions
one through five,
and we'll do maybe I think
I think I've only did 1 or 2.
Yeah, we only did one emotion.
So maybe we'll do two.
But let's do happy again.
Let's show happy as your characters.
So we have IL as happy and
we have our Lucchino happy.
So happy at one.
Two. Three.
Four.
Five.
Hey happiness.
Great, great.
All right.
So let's let's shake it off.
Really shake it off a little bit.
Get to get neutral. Get to neutral.
And let's do a different
let's do a different emotion.
Let's do confused. Right.
Because I think both of these characters
have really interesting confused.
So confused at one. Two.
Three.
Four.
Five.
All the confusion.
Oh my god, oh my God.
I was gonna have it.
All right. Yeah.
Fantastic. Fantastic. Did we.
I just want to reach out
to the audience, see,
what did you notice between Mark and Rob
and their avatars?
What did you see?
That was maybe a little different
or maybe the same that you didn't expect?
That translated very naturally.
Anybody want to participate?
You can just shout it out.
Since there's so few of us,
we can have a really fun conversation.
The tales are a blast. Yeah
they are okay.
That's an extended emotional emote.
Yes. Yeah, absolutely.
The tails and the ears.
We have some people who have ears where
if you touch them, they, they per
but that's a whole other thing.
Anyone else?
Anyone else sees something that is like,
oh wow, that looked very similar
to what they were doing.
Or I didn't expect that.
There's something about the
the height and like a set of the avatars
that attached to the characters
really, really well with,
to use your delightful language,
the big wigs as Mark's avatar
and the sort of zany goofballs
as Rob's avatar, who's,
you know, a little shorter,
a little stylistically cuter.
And then also,
I associate such specific movements with,
with, like
each of these characters from,
you know, learning them and whatever.
And the movements are different,
but also equally specific in VR, which.
Is talk
more about that and talk more about that.
Yeah.
Like the I mean, you associate
like each character with a specific way
they carry themselves right here, either
carrying with your nose or your chin
or your chest or your pelvis
or your stomach.
Right.
Like the way that these characters move
in real life
in quotes, space is so specific.
And comedia,
as we learn it, sort of initially.
And it's there.
The movements
for each of these characters in VR
space is different, but equally specific,
like they're making different choices
for their characters,
but they're still making such like
physically specific choices
for their characters that identify them.
Yes, exactly.
So that is that's the thing,
is that where we see
limitations in VR,
we need to look for opportunities.
And so if we can't show that our noses up,
how else do we show that
if we can't show that we're hunched over,
how else do we show that?
And we can also use our voice in
in this as well.
So there are a lot of places to explore
that if you can't have the thing.
Exactly how you like it.
What can you do to get what you want?
And that's why we spend so much time
in front of the mirror saying,
oh, it doesn't look like that.
Oh, it doesn't translate.
Oh, but if I do that and then I do this
and then I change my voice,
then I have that reaction.
So it is not just acting, it isn't just
putting a headset on an acting.
This is actually a whole new approach
to acting.
This is a whole new need it.
I mean, VR theater does exist.
There needs to be training
within this space because it's
not just given actor and headset
and they know what to do.
And I could Mandy. Yeah.
Yes yes. Yes
I'll do another character.
We and also there's something that happens
with the headset that you become
paralyzed really quickly
as soon as because your,
your entire attention is going to
your visual cortex, your entire attention.
And so you, you know,
you do that whole like I'm
in front of a computer,
I don't have a body anymore business.
Right.
This a lot of great thinkers
have have worked against.
So Mandy has helped us so much to like,
put us back into our bodies.
Well.
Okay.
And so we're going to do another thing.
Which one more
and then we'll get to a scene.
We're going to play another physical
comedy practice called $5 Bill.
And it's when you walk down the street
and you see a $5 bill,
how do you pick it up?
But more importantly,
how do these characters pick it up?
Do they?
I'm not.
I won't even say anything
because I wouldn't want you to see how
they have kind of translated
their particular character
to find a $5 bill on the street,
and what do they do with it?
We all do something differently,
and if you don't think so,
you need to think about that
a little more.
All right. So let's go.
Let's start.
Who's ready first.
Rob is ready after Rob.
Rob is ready. Okay.
Funny. Zany, probably poor.
Probably looking for things.
To other other things. On the street.
My servant must go before.
Clearly after. You.
Are looking.
Is walking down the street
and sees a $5 bill.
And please again check Rob out.
Watch Rob and his avatar
and how it's different or the same.
Scene.
Yay! So
it looked like you were very excited.
Rob is that right?
Rob you need to unmute, I think.
Oh, you're you're oh yeah you are.
Well that's okay because.
I was going to say
let's ask the audience what they saw.
What did the audience see.
I like I like how he saw it.
And then he when he went to get it,
his little tail went way up in the air.
In. This super expressive thing
of picking that $5 bill up, you know,
we could feel it in this whole body.
And what did anybody else. See.
I like there's like
a scattered movement thing
that Rob is doing with this character
that I really like.
It was showing up in the happy
exercise to,
but that like, it's
almost like blending the animal avatar
with the zanni physicality
where you're like running across the room
and kind of looking about,
yeah, you're scurrying.
Yeah, yeah.
Exactly what you didn't hear Rob say.
And I'm glad that you didn't,
because I was like, oh,
I should ask the audience with
these offers before we even hear from Rob.
So, Rob, why don't you share with us
what you were doing?
Yeah, I guess, yes.
It's fun to hear that.
That that's that
I was going for a kind of disjointed,
even though it's a squirrel avatar.
My understanding of part
of the tradition of the zines
is there more like sort of chickens?
And I was looking around,
so trying to do a bit of random
chicken
walk, do the classic thing of passing it,
not believing, you know, coming back
to see if that's really what I saw.
And then a lot of concern about who else
might be seeing or if it was a trap.
It's like classic comedy things.
Well, I love it.
So just to share with everybody
one of the.
One of the.
One of the last session
we had, Rob actually ate the $5
bill. So.
But what was interesting is
he didn't mean to it to do that
because he
I think, Rob, you brought it to your face.
And I was like, what are you doing?
You're eating it because this is the thing
is, as you see in my,
my box, my, my hands are on my mouth.
But in VR,
my hands are not in my mouth, on my mouth.
So to have it on my mouth,
I'd actually have
to put my hands on my headset.
So if you see that,
if I'm if I have to cover my face,
I actually have to really
bring my hands up here.
And so I wasn't sure what Rob was doing
the last session.
I'm like, did you eat it?
And he's like, I was just looking at it,
but yes, and did it.
And yes, I ate it. And then.
But then we discussed to show
that you've eaten something.
What could you do?
So maybe it's so good, you know,
you know, tapping your stomach to indicate
that you've just eaten something
to make sure there's no ambiguity of what
you're communicating to your audience.
So it's about distilling
those little moments that we think
we know what we're saying
and to understand
what else can we add to it
to make sure it's crystal clear.
These are things that physical comedians
work on anyway.
When you talk to improvisers about doing,
doing, I can't think of it right now.
But when you know,
when they're eating something
or they're washing dishes,
they want to make sure everything's
very clear.
And, and so it's the same,
the same thing that will be
that we're doing in,
in VR
as in the real world,
but just with a little difference.
And I see that Rob has left
the left the arena.
But that's okay because. So sometimes.
When the when the VR freezes.
So I'll be I'll be rejoining. Okay.
So sometimes we lose people
and that's something that we have to deal
with when we are performing.
We have to
think about what happens when we crash
so we could lose internet service.
Somebody could
somebody batteries could run out.
If they're using a quest like Rob and
Mark, and we just have to work with it.
So that's something we don't have to worry
about on stage as much.
I mean, people have emergencies, yes,
but people don't disappear.
They don't just like fall into the ether,
which is what we have here.
So really, we prepare by making strategies
of what happens
when somebody loses power, when somebody
is, you know, gets kicked off the network.
How do we respond to that?
So we build that into all of our training.
So while we're waiting for Rob to come
back, let's have Mark find a $5 bill as.
Great.
What do we see real quick.
What do we see real quick?
Anybody see anything.
There's still that good old manufactured
dignity and.
I like that.
The little bit of sneaky trying to grab it
and tuck it
as soon as possible was fun to.
Nobody saw this.
Anyone else?
Totally fine.
Some of the things that we've I've done in
the past
is also tripping so we can.
What we do is it's very similar to
and you can do this in three point
tracking to physical
comedy is you don't actually trip yourself
because you will fall.
And we don't want that.
We want to pose the illusion.
So we I have my students trip
as their character.
I asked them what would your character do?
So if they trip, do they look back?
Do they yell what's. Going on?
Or do they tell people about it?
Hey everybody!
Look, the thing. I almost tripped on it.
Do they laugh?
Do they take a bow?
You know, there's so many different ways
that you can kind of express
your character and what they would do
in a certain situation
that could then add on to your physical
of your
of your character and your your space.
I invited Rob back.
Rob has not joined us yet.
It's getting there.
You're getting there.
We probably have real quick.
I know we're we're running out of time
here, but.
What is your end time? Is it?
It's one minute. 313.
Oh, wait. I got to try the trip. Mandy,
even though we.
Oh, you want to try the trip? Okay.
Why don't you try the trip?
Oh, wait, wait.
Okay.
Trip.
What was it?
Okay.
And seen.
So one thing we noticed that
we're three point tracking.
I'm just going to give it to you right now
since we.
We're out of time is the hands.
So you can show with your hands
and your body you can move forward
and not really trip.
Right.
But you can give that intention
or that impression to your audience.
You never want your audience to feel
that you are actually in danger,
because then they disconnect
from the moment.
And so
by establishing,
no, I'm fine, I'm fine,
but it was a close one.
You can do that with all your body,
but not actually trip.
And so for three point trackers that's
that's really easy to do.
Rob you look very very wary.
You can start.
Are you ready?
Yeah I couldn't
it's the usual problems like I,
I didn't see the invite or I couldn't,
I couldn't find an invite, but no.
It's okay.
But anyway, we're at time anyway, so.
We're at time.
But you all worked so hard.
Oh, it's so much fun.
Thank you so much.
Thank you. Mandy. Mandy! You're awesome.
You are awesome.
That was really cool, you guys.
I'm. I'm excited to see what you might do
next.
I'm using the technology
that now you you, you're
beginning to get a handle
on, you know, for Robin and Mark.
But, Mandy, what's your vision?
Is there a cool
thing you'd like to do next,
with or without Mark and run. Up.
With them, I hope.
Well, yeah.
Hopefully
we're we're talking about devising a show
and so that is in the works.
And then I am always doing choreography
with the VR Dance Academy.
So just finding ways
that we can push dance forward in VR,
even on a stage, using things
that we wouldn't be able to use
because we perform on a stage in VR.
Our students are very new to dance,
and so we want to give them
that opportunity to perform on stage
that everyone loves to do.
And so we find ways to kind of make
it more a lot more fun, right.
So we'll we'll find kind of effects
that we can use that we would not be able
to use in a real stage
because it's just way too expensive.
So we have our stage and we're able
to kind of give the students
this really interesting opportunity
of performing on stage with a lot of like,
high tech stuff
that probably only Broadway can do.
Not not a little dance company like us.
And then, yeah,
I have different projects I'm working on.
And then I have a project
I did a prototype for a few years ago
that I hoped to one day do in full,
and that's
kind of on the on the horizon.
Yeah. This was awesome.
Thank you so much for sharing.
Yeah, thanks for having us. I think we.
We unfortunately
do I think need to close the room up
so we can get it ready for the next.
All right.
But I'm delighted.
I can't wait to see where
this goes and hear more about it.
Yeah.
And are you guys going to be
on the discord
and talking at all on the discord
for people who are interested?
Yeah. Why don't we?
Why don't we go to the cafe
channel on the discord?
And Mandy, if you can, you can.
You want to join us there? Yeah, sure.
I think I may need to go to my next panel.
Okay. Marks on a panel marks another time.
Well,
anyway, we'll catch up you guys very soon.
Yeah.
Shot a screenshot.
That would be awesome.
Yeah. Heck, yeah.
Oh, okay. Great. Awesome.
All right.
Bye, everybody.
Thank you. Thanks, Alyssa.
Thanks for coming.
I took a few screenshots
during your thing. Yay!
Thank you. Okay.
Take care.
I'll send them.
Thank you. Mandy. By.